Guide to the John Sylvester Fischer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1928-1978, undated; Series IV; 4.75 lienar feet (12 boxes, microfilm)
  - Articles
    - "England's Pink Party", 1935 March (Box 45, Folder 97)
    - Forward (edited by J. Fischer), 1935 March (Box 45, Folder 98)
    - "How Little is Little England?", 1935 October (Box 45, Folder 99)
    - "The Task of the Farm Security Administration," [The New Democracy?], 1937 October 8 (Box 45, Folder 100)
    - [untitled article re the Punjab], [ca.1943-1945] (Box 45, Folder 101)
    - "Vinegar Joe's Problem,", 1944 December (Box 45, Folder 102)
    - "The Future Defense of the U.S.A.,", 1945 January (Box 45, Folder 103)
    - "India's Insoluble Hunger,", 1945 April (Box 45, Folder 104)
    - "The Army Takes Over,", 1945 May (Box 45, Folder 105)
    - "World Trade: Tomorrow's Problem," Transatlantic, 1945 July (Box 45, Folder 106)
    - "Odds Against Another War,", 1945 August (Box 45, Folder 107)
    - "For Love of Lord Louis," Town & Country, 1945 September (Box 45, Folder 108)
    - "Let's Go Back to the Spoils System,", 1945 October (Box 45, Folder 109)
    - "Closing a Deal in Kapurthala," The New Yorker, 1945 November 3 (Box 45, Folder 110)
    - "Truman: A Little West of Center,", 1945 December (Box 45, Folder 111)
    - "Mr. Truman Reorganizes,", 1946 January (Box 45, Folder 112)
    - "Is Truman a Failure?,", 1946 April (Box 45, Folder 113)
    - "India's Treasures Helped the Allies," National Geographic, 1946 April (Box 45, Folder 114)
    - "The Scared Men in the Kremlin,", 1946 August (Box 45, Folder 115)
    - "No Rest for the Weary Russians,", 1946 September (Box 45, Folder 116)
    - "The Ukraine," Life, 1946 October 28 (Box 45, Folder 117)
    - "Russia's Ruling Class,", 1946 October (Box 45, Folder 118)
    - "Six-Disillusioned Comrades," The Saturday Review, 1947 April 5 (Box 45, Folder 119)
    - "Ukrainian Shadow," The New Yorker, 1947 April 12 (Box 45, Folder 120)
    - "The Lost Liberals,", 1947 May (Box 45, Folder 121)
    - "La Vie en U.R.S.S.," Revue de Paris, 1947 May (Box 45, Folder 122)
    - "The Classless Society, Kind of," Pageant, 1947 September (Box 45, Folder 123)
    - "Spain: A Diplomatic Case History," The Nation, 1948 June 19 (Box 45, Folder 124)
    - "War Within a War," The Nation, 1948 October 16 (Box 45, Folder 125)
    - "Unwritten Rules of American Politics,", 1948 November (Box 45, Folder 126)
    - "Truman & Co., Limited,", 1949 July (Box 45, Folder 127)
    - "Insomnia in Whitehall,", 1950 January (Box 45, Folder 128)
    - "General MacArthur," The New Statesman and Nation, 1951 May 12 (Box 45, Folder 129)
    - "The German Booby Trap,", 1951 May (Box 45, Folder 130)
    - "Mr. Truman's Politburo,", 1951 June (Box 45, Folder 131)
    - "A Step Toward Lasting Peace," Catholic Digest, 1952 February (Box 45, Folder 132)
    - "What Do the Democrats Do Now?,", 1953 March (Box 45, Folder 133)
    - "Who's a Reactionary?" The Reporter, 1953 October 13 (Box 45, Folder 134)
    - "A Matter of Labels," The American Scholar, [1953?] (Box 45, Folder 135)
    - "The Balancing of Interest Groups in a Federal System," Columbia University Bicentennial Conference, 1954 June 11-14 (Box 46, Folder 136)
    - "The Loving Care of Determined Women," Man Against Woman, edited by Charles Neider, 1957, 1955 (Box 46, Folder 137)
    - "Remembrance in a High Valley,", 1956 May (Box 46, Folder 138)
    - "The New Need for Leaders," The Rotarian, 1956 August (Box 46, Folder 139)
    - "Are You a Political Morning-Glory?" Woman's Day, 1956 September (Box 46, Folder 140)
    - "The Harm Good People Do,", 1956 October (Box 46, Folder 141)
    - "Conversation at Midnight,", 1958 January (Box 46, Folder 142)
    - "Self-Portrait of the Harper Reader,", 1958 September (Box 46, Folder 143)
    - 'Three Valentines,", 1959 February (Box 46, Folder 144)
    - "TV and Its Critics,", 1959 July (Box 46, Folder 145)
    - "Christmas List,", 1959 December (Box 46, Folder 146)
    - "The Age of Mobility," American Petroleum Institute Quarterly, 1959 (Box 46, Folder 147)
    - "Please Don't Bite the Politicians,", 1960 November (Box 46, Folder 148)
    - "Foreward," The Crisis in American Medicine, edited by Marion K. Saunders, 1960 (Box 46, Folder 149)
    - "Point of No Return? A Puzzled Report from Yugoslavia,", 1961 July (Box 46, Folder 150)
    - "A Hopeful Letter to Fowler Hamilton, 1961 November (Box 46, Folder 151)
    - "What the Negro Needs Most: A First-Class Citizens' Council,", 1962 July (Box 46, Folder 152)
    - "The Stupidity Problem,", 1962 (Box 46, Folder 153)
    - "What Women Can Do for Peace,", 1963 April (Box 46, Folder 154)
    - "An Unfashionable Kind of Historian," The Texas Observer, 1963 July 26 (Box 46, Folder 155)
    - "On the Rationality of the Arms Race: Correspondence Between Bertrand Russell and John Fischer,", 1963 July (Box 46, Folder 156)
    - "Helping Hand for a Literary Upstart,", 1963 September (Box 46, Folder 157)
    - "Myths about Publishing,", 1963 (Box 46, Folder 158)
    - "Why Nobody Can't Write Good,", 1964 February (Box 46, Folder 159)
    - "The Japanese Intellectuals,", 1964 September (Box 46, Folder 160)
    - "Is There a Teacher on the Faculty?,", 1965 February (Box 46, Folder 161)
    - "The Editor's Trade,", 1965 July (Box 46, Folder 162)
    - "James Bond, Mr. Johnson, and the Intellectuals,", 1965 August (Box 46, Folder 163)
    - "Substitutes for Violence,", 1966 January (Box 46, Folder 164)
    - "Letter to a New Leftist, From a Tired Liberal,", 1966 March (Box 46, Folder 165)
    - "Field Notes on the Europeans,", 1967 March (Box 46, Folder 166)
    - "Field Notes on the Europeans: Part II,", 1967 May (Box 46, Folder 167)
    - "Announcing Some Changes,", 1967 July (Box 46, Folder 168)
    - "Four Choices for Young People,", 1967 August (Box 46, Folder 169)
    - "He Liked Students," The Teacher, edited by Morris L. Ernst, 1967 (Box 46, Folder 170)
    - "A Shipload of Doomed Men,", 1968 January (Box 46, Folder 171)
    - "The Perils of Publishing: How to Tell When You Are Being Corrupted,", 1968 May (Box 46, Folder 172)
    - "Western Intellectuals Vs. Myrdal's Brutal Facts,", 1968 June (Box 46, Folder 173)
    - "The Case for Rebellious Students and Their Counterrevolution,", 1968 August (Box 46, Folder 174)
    - "Open Letter to the Next President,", 1968 September (Box 46, Folder 175)
    - "Can Ralph R. Widner Save New York, Chicago, and Detroit?,", 1968 October (Box 46, Folder 176)
    - "The Lazarus Twins in Pennsylvania: How Scranton and Wilkins-Barre Are Rising from the Dead,", 1968 November (Box 46, Folder 177)
    - "Christmas List,", 1968 December (Box 46, Folder 178)
    - "Open Letter to a Girl Agast": draft, [1968?] (Box 46, Folder 179)
    - "Letter from Leete's Island,", 1969 January (Box 46, Folder 180)
    - "The Minnesota Experiment: How To Make a Big City Fit to Live In,", 1969 April (Box 46, Folder 181)
    - "Seattle's Modern-Day Vigilantes,", 1969 May (Box 46, Folder 181a)
    - "A Different Kind of Campus,", 1969 July (Box 46, Folder 182)
    - "Survival U: Prospectus for a Really Relevant University,", 1969 September (Box 46, Folder 183)
    - "Contrary Spirits,", 1969 October (Box 46, Folder 184)
    - "Planning for the Second America,", 1969 November (Box 46, Folder 185)
    - "Notes from the Underground,", 1970 February (Box 47, Folder 186)
    - "How I Got Radicalized,", 1970 April (Box 47, Folder 187)
    - "What am I Doing Here? (apologia pro Februa Sua),", 1970 May (Box 47, Folder 188)
    - "Preface to the Catalogue of Curmudgeon College,", 1970 June (Box 47, Folder 189)
    - "Mark Rothko: Portrait of the Artist as an Angry Man,", 1970 July (Box 47, Folder 190)
    - "Outwitting Wall Street,", 1970 September (Box 47, Folder 191)
    - "Black Panthers and Their White Hero-Worshipers,", 1970 September (Box 47, Folder 192)
    - "Can the Nixon Administration Be Doing Something Right?,", 1970 November (Box 47, Folder 193)
    - "Christmas List,", 1970 December (Box 47, Folder 194)
    - "Survival U. is Alive and Burgeoning in Green Bay, Wisconsin,", 1971 February (Box 47, Folder 195)
    - "After the Revolution: the End of the Age of Affluence,", 1971 March (Box 47, Folder 196)
    - "A Modest Contribution to the Marijuana and Folklore Industries,", 1971 April (Box 47, Folder 197)
    - "Jacksonville: So Different You Can Hardly Believe It,", 1971 July (Box 47, Folder 198)
    - "Women's Lib and the Caperton Girls,", 1972 February (Box 47, Folder 199)
    - "Georgia: Mother of Social Invention,", 1972 March (Box 47, Folder 200)
    - "Field Notes on the Changing South,", 1972 April (Box 47, Folder 201)
    - "Getting Stingy,", 1972 April (Box 47, Folder 202)
    - "Portugal Tries to Wake Up,", 1972 July (Box 47, Folder 203)
    - "Headnote TK,", 1972 September (Box 47, Folder 204)
    - "A Dirge for DeVoto and the New Heresy of Light Whiskey,", 1972 November (Box 47, Folder 205)
    - "Christmas List: A Few Hints for Hark,", 1972 December (Box 47, Folder 206)
    - "A Case of Termination,", 1973 February (Box 47, Folder 207)
    - "American Culture at the Crossroads," House Beautiful, 1973 March (Box 47, Folder 208)
    - "A Threat of Death by Mail,", 1973 May (Box 47, Folder 209)
    - "Vital Signs,", 1974 August (Box 47, Folder 210)
    - "The Real Greening of America," National Civic Review, 1975 March (Box 47, Folder 211)
    - "The Rescue of Jacksonville," Planning, 1975 May (Box 47, Folder 212)
    - "In Some Areas Today's Temperature is 98.6," New York Times, 1975 August 1 (Box 47, Folder 213)
    - "125th Anniversary Piece,", [1975] (Box 47, Folder 214)
    - "Advice to Young Writers," Bookletter, 1976 January 5 (Box 47, Folder 215)
    - "The Development Districts and the Next Ten Years," Appalachia, 1976 February-March (Box 47, Folder 216)
    - "Spaces for the Weary,", 1978 May (Box 47, Folder 217)
    - "Barbed Wire.And the Art of Stringing It,", 1978 July (Box 47, Folder 218)
    - "Aloneness,", undated (Box 47, Folder 219)
    - "The Masses and the Arts," Yale Review, undated (Box 47, Folder 220)
    - "This Hurts Me More Than It Hurts Mr. Harrington,", undated (Box 47, Folder 221)
    - "Why Some People Don't Buy Harper's,", undated (Box 47, Folder 222)
    - Untitled and incomplete, undated (Box 47, Folder 223)
  - Speeches
    - "Third Parties and the American Political Tradition," Kenyon College Conference: The Heritage of the English-Speaking Peoples and Their Responsibility, 1947 September (Box 48, Folder 224)
    - "American Commentary….for BBC,", 1950 March 29 (Box 48, Folder 225)
    - "American Commentary….for BBC,", 1950 May 3 (Box 48, Folder 226)
    - "Writers, Publishers, and Their Customers," Bread Loaf Writers' Conference, Middlebury College, 1952 August 14 (Box 48, Folder 227)
    - "The Balancing of Interest Groups in a Federal System," Columbia University Conference on Federalism, Arden House, 1954 January 11 (Box 48, Folder 228)
    - "The American Heresy," Kenyon College, 1954 June 14 (Box 48, Folder 229)
    - Address, Bucknell University Annual Convocation, 1954 September 29 (Box 48, Folder 230)
    - "The American Heresy," White Plains Community Church, 1955 May 15 (Box 48, Folder 231)
    - Commencement address, University of Massachusetts, 1956 June 3 (Box 48, Folder 232)
    - Address, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, 1957 May 14 (Box 48, Folder 233)
    - Address, American Association of Museums Annual Meeting, Charleston, South Carolina, 1958 May 1 (Box 48, Folder 234)
    - "Writers, Publishers, and the Reading Public," Southwestern Library Association, Galveston, Texas, 1958 October 24 (Box 48, Folder 235)
    - "The American Pyramids," Zisking Lectures, Smith College, 1958 December 3-4 (Box 48, Folder 236)
    - "Economics and Structure of the Minority Magazine," Annenberg School of Communications, University of Pennsylvania, 1959 December 3 (Box 48, Folder 237)
    - Hearing testimony, Federal Communications commission, 1959 December 14 (Box 48, Folder 238)
    - "Museums and Their Publics," Writers Art Gallery, Baltimore, Maryland, 1960 May 23 (Box 48, Folder 239)
    - Commencement address, Solebury School, 1960 June 11 (Box 48, Folder 240)
    - "The Seven Lively Arts," Williamsburg International Assembly, 1961 June 14 (Box 48, Folder 241)
    - Address, Public Relations Society of America Institute, Cornell University, 1961 August 10 (Box 48, Folder 242)
    - Address, Oberlin College and Penn State University, 1961 October 26, 1962 October 26 (Box 48, Folder 243)
    - Department of Journalism Lecture, University of California at Berkeley, 1962 January 4 (Box 48, Folder 244)
    - Address, Magazine Promotion Group, 1962 August 29 (Box 48, Folder 245)
    - "Magazine and Newspaper Journalism: A Comparison," Sixteenth Annual Newspaper Guild Memorial Lecture, University of Minnesota, 1962 October 11 (Box 48, Folder 246)
    - Commencement address, Radcliffe College, 1964 June 10 (Box 48, Folder 247)
    - "The Open Mind: A Profile of John Fischer," NBC Television, 1965 April 11 (Box 48, Folder 247a)
    - The Student's Responsibility for Higher Education," Encyclopedia Britannica Lectures, University of Chicago, 1965 May 6 (Box 48, Folder 248)
    - Address, Magazine Publishers Association, 1966 November 29 (Box 48, Folder 249)
    - "Four Choices for Young People," Stanford University, 1967 June 18 (Box 49, Folder 250)
    - Address, Great Editors Seminar, American Society of Magazine Editors, New York, 1967 October 23 (Box 49, Folder 251)
    - "European Integration," National Conference on European Integration, University of Pennsylvania, 1968 March 22 (Box 49, Folder 252)
    - "Innovations in Government," University of California at Santa Cruz, 1969 February 10, 17, 24 (Box 49, Folder 253)
    - "Innovations in Government," 1969 National Planning Conference of the American Society of Planning Officials, Cincinnati, Ohio, 1969 April 21 (Box 49, Folder 254)
    - "The Next Thirty Years," Brown and Haley Lectures, University of Puget Sound, 1970 March 10-12 (Box 49, Folder 255)
    - "Can Local Government Be Revived?," Duke University, 1971 November 29 (Box 49, Folder 256)
    - "Statement before the Senate Committee on Public Works concerning S.3381, a bill to establish a national development program,", 1972 April 25 (Box 49, Folder 257)
    - "Statement for the Senate Post Office and Civil Service Committee,", undated (Box 49, Folder 258)
    - Commencement address, Solebury School, undated (Box 49, Folder 259)
- Diaries and Other Memorabilia, 1910-1980, undated; Series V; 2 linear feet (5 boxes, 1 folio)
  The contents of this series are grouped by type. Each type of material is arranged chronologically.
  - Diaries
    - 1925 February 25-1926 January 14 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - 1926 April 27-1927 August 27 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - 1927 October 1-1928 March 20 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - 1928 March 25-1929 January 17 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - 1929 January 21-1929 October 27 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - 1929 October 28-1933 August 21 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - 1933 August 26-1934 September 23 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Travel journals
    - India, [ca. 1943-1944] (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Ukraine, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 9-10)
    - Greece, 1959 (Box 51, Folder 11)
    - Yugoslavia, 1961 (Box 51, Folder 12)
    - Iran and Japan, 1964 (Box 51, Folder 13)
    - Japan, 1964 (Box 51, Folder 14)
    - Europe, 1966 (Box 51, Folder 15)
    - Portugal, 1972 (Box 51, Folder 16)
    - England, 1975 (Box 51, Folder 17)
  - Account books, 1928-1932 (Box 51, Folder 18)
  - Datebooks, 1965, 1970, 1975-1977 (Box 51, Folder 19-20)
  - Notebooks and school papers, 1923-1928 (Box 51, Folder 21-25)
  - Notebooks and school papers, [ca. 1928-1932]-1967, undated (Box 52, Folder 26-34)
  - Photographs, 1930-1957, undated (Box 53, Folder 35)
  - Newspaper clippings about John Fischer and family, 1920-1980, undated (Box 53, Folder 36-41)
  - Memorabilia, 1910-1935 (Box 53, Folder 42-46)
  - Memorabilia, 1935-1976, undated (Box 54, Folder 47-52)
  - Biographical sketches, [ca. 1940-1956] (Box 54, Folder 53)
  - Memorial tributes, obituaries, 1978 (Box 54, Folder 54)
  - Diplomas and certificates, 1919-1967,1979, undated (Box 61)
- Yale Files, 1944, 1961-1973, undated; Series VI; 2.5 linear feet (6 boxes)
  This series begins with three folders of notes and seminar papers, but the bulk of the series is printed material organized alphabetically by topic.
  - Notes, 1967-1969 (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Notes: Edie MacMullen, undated (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Seminar papers, 1969 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Agricultural policy, 1965-1968 (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Alabama, 1968 (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - Appalachian regional development, 1967-1968 (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Bibliographies, [ca. 1967-1969] (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - Cities, optimum size, 1963-1970 (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - City-County mergers, undated (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - Coastal Plains Regional Commission, 1967-1969 (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - Counties, 1961, 1966 (Box 55, Folder 11)
  - Detroit, 1972 (Box 55, Folder 12)
  - East Cleveland, 1969 (Box 56, Folder 13)
  - Ecology, 1963, 1967-1970 (Box 56, Folder 14)
  - Federal regions, 1970-1972 (Box 56, Folder 15)
  - Four Corners Regional Commission, 1967-1969 (Box 56, Folder 16)
  - Georgia, 1968-1969 (Box 56, Folder 17)
  - Housing, 1969-1970 (Box 56, Folder 18)
  - Indiana, 1969-1970 (Box 56, Folder 19)
  - Indians, 1969 (Box 56, Folder 20)
  - Jacksonville (Florida), 1969-1973 (Box 56, Folder 21)
  - Kentucky, 1967-1969 (Box 56, Folder 22)
  - Location of industry, 1967-1968 (Box 56, Folder 23)
  - Maryland, 1967-1969 (Box 56, Folder 24)
  - Metropolitan planning, 1963, 1967-1970 (Box 56, Folder 25)
  - Miami, 1967-1969 (Box 57, Folder 26)
  - Migration, 1965-1968 (Box 57, Folder 27)
  - Minnesota, 1968-1969 (Box 57, Folder 28)
  - Nashville, 1968-1969 (Box 57, Folder 29)
  - National Municipal League, 1944, 1968-1969 (Box 57, Folder 30)
  - New England Regional Commission, 1967-1968 (Box 57, Folder 31)
  - New Jersey, 1968 (Box 57, Folder 32)
  - New York, 1967-1971 (Box 57, Folder 33)
  - North Carolina, 1966-1967 (Box 57, Folder 34)
  - Oklahoma, 1967-1969 (Box 57, Folder 35)
  - Ozarks Regional Commission, 1966-1969 (Box 57, Folder 36)
  - Pennsylvania, 1967-1973, undated (Box 57, Folder 37)
  - Pennsylvania, 1967-1969, undated (Box 58, Folder 38-41)
  - Portland (Oregon), undated (Box 59, Folder 42)
  - President's Task Force on Government Organization, 1967 (Box 59, Folder 43)
  - Regional planning, 1967-1973 (Box 59, Folder 44)
  - Regions—general, 1968-1970 (Box 59, Folder 45)
  - San Francisco, 1969-1970 (Box 59, Folder 46)
  - Seattle, 1967-1973 (Box 59, Folder 47)
  - South Carolina, 1967-1968 (Box 59, Folder 48)
  - States, 1966-1970 (Box 59, Folder 49)
  - Taxes and finance, 1968-1973 (Box 59, Folder 50)
  - Tennessee and Tennessee Valley Authority, 1967-1968 (Box 60, Folder 51)
  - Total Education in the Total Environment, [ca. 1970] (Box 60, Folder 53)
  - Transportation, 1967-1969 (Box 60, Folder 54)
  - Upper Great Lakes Regional Commission, 1967-1969 (Box 60, Folder 55)
  - Urban Coalition, 1969 (Box 60, Folder 56)
  - Urban decentralization, 1967, 1972 (Box 60, Folder 57)
  - Urban growth policy, 1972 (Box 60, Folder 58)
  - Urban Institute, 1968-1970 (Box 60, Folder 59)
  - Utah, 1968-1969 (Box 60, Folder 60)
  - Toronto, 1963-1972 (Box 60, Folder 52)
  - Virginia, 1968-1969 (Box 60, Folder 61)
  - Washington, D.C, .1966-1968 (Box 60, Folder 62)
  - Welfare, 1969 (Box 60, Folder 63)
  - West Virginia, undated (Box 60, Folder 64)
  - Wisconsin, 1968-1969 (Box 60, Folder 65)